this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio dotnet. se radio brings you.
relevant and detailed discussions of software engineering topics at least once a month.
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E software magazine online at computer or / software.
for software engineering radio this is Stefan toca.
today I'm joined by Mark Nottingham, mark is a very well known figure in Internet standardization.
he has been an editor and co-author for numerous standards such as ws addressing, the atom syndication format, WEP linking and many more.
most recently he has been chairing the IETF s working group on the web's core protocol HTTP.
leading built the revision of the HTTP 1.1 specification as well as the introduction of the first new major version in years HTTP 2.
which is going to be today's main topic.
he has also recently been elected a member of a w3c stek nickel architecture group.
which his architectural guidance to all the various working groups creating specifications at the web standardization body.
so welcome mark to this new episode of SC radio.
and as usual I'd like to start by asking you to introduce yourself.
okay my name is Mark Nottingham and I chair the HTTP working group in the ITF and I'm also a member of the w3c technical architecture group.
so can you tell us a little bit about what the IETF and the w3c actually do.
so they're both technical standards bodies.
so the IETF is has been around for a long time, and they were the body that originally took charge of forming and standardizing the internet.
a lot of the internet pioneers helped to put the IETF together.
and then from my standpoint it's the body that owns HT to the protocol HTTP.
the w3c is the body that owns it's an industry consortium which is a little bit different but much the same that effectively owns the web itself.
and so that was put together by Tim berners-lee a few years after he you know after the web really took off.
okay so the topic we're going to talk about is HTTP, more specifically HTTP 2.
so before we go into the details of this new version maybe you can give our listeners a brief introduction to HTTP.
which seems like something everybody should know, but maybe nobody really or some people at least do not really know.
from and from more standards point of view yeah everyone uses it I think or almost everyone, but the deeper you go the more you find I suppose.
I still find things that are new to me about it all the time.
so yeah it's it's the core protocol of the web.
you know we say the web is built on three different things on identifiers so URLs your eyes and formats like HTML.
and then protocols and HTTP is the predominant protocol for for the web.
and it's called it stands for a hypertext Transfer Protocol so HTTP.
and many people confuse that with transport transfer is in danger.
you're transferring what we used to call entities or you're transferring payloads are around back and forth between the client and server.
whereas a transport protocol is a much lower layer thing it's like TCP or UDP.
and so that's it it's it's you know one of the legs that the web stands on.
it's it's been around since Tim came up with it in the early 90s and it's been through a number of revisions since then.
the most recent is is what you want to talk about HTTP -.
I'd like to talk about some of those things that seem entirely obvious but maybe aren't.
so maybe it should be obvious what a protocol is, but you know it's not.
what what what does the term protocol actually mean.
so there's there's a lot of history behind that in terms of diplomacy and and so forth.
but but in computer protocols it's it's you know how do how do two machines or two entities talking in this case over a network.
usually HTTP was designed mostly to be a network protocol.
but Roy fielding one of the primary authors of HTTP 1.1 will go out of his way to point out it's not just for networking.
it's also for things like running off of a cd-rom drive or in other contexts.
you can you know think of the model of HTTP is there's a client in the server.
how do you fetch things off of the server to get them to your web browser.
in the common case HTTP is used for lots of other things, but but really web browsers is the primary use case.
so in terms of gonna what is the HTTP protocol.
it's the way that your web browser asks a web server for what it needs to show you a web page.
mm-hmm so maybe let's get more into this transfer and transport distinction.
so what actually is it that a Transfer Protocol adds to a transport protocol.
so it's interesting you know a transport protocol is a fairly low layer thing.
yeah I won't call it dumb, but but from an application standpoint it doesn't give you a lot.
and that's not to denigrate what for example TCP does there's a tremendous amount of value and.
and complexity in what TCP does in terms of giving you this this ordered reliable stream of information.
but it doesn't give you a lot to hang on to as an application, you need to build things on top of that.
so HTTP gives you a way to think about how for example one message is delimited from another message.
so you can tell the difference between one request and the next request on a connection.
it gives you things like caching and and a common vocabulary to talk about what you want to do.
and really that's what protocol is is it's a shared vocabulary shared way of communicating.
and and the abstraction in HTTP is is fairly high-level.
and then you have a common set of methods you don't get post put delete and a bunch more.
you have these message buddies that you can sling around and have metadata to talk about those messages bodies and the HTTP headers.
things like content type and you know lots of other things that we've added to it over the years.
and then you have the responses in the status code that tell you you know what the high level semantics the meaning of that response is.
so it was 200 ok to mean that it's OK and that this is what you asked for.
and 500 means that the server had a problem and it can't give you what you asked for.
and all those different things that that you know HTTP gives you in terms of methods and headers.
and his codes and formality around the bodies gives you the ability to build applications more easily.
if you had to create all of that from scratch as a developer then then you'd spend a lot of time getting it right.
HTTP is something you can just grab off of the shelf and reuse in your application, and it usually works pretty well.
I guess you know for for folks who are familiar with it the interesting contrast is with something called WebSockets.
WebSockets came around a few years ago and and it is a much lower it's still an application protocol like HTTP is, but it's a much lower level of abstraction.
it's much lower value in that sense it's basically TCP strapped on to the web.
so you just get a bi-directional ordered string reliable streaming anything and and between the client in the server.
and WebSockets you know what would I talk to people about it there are a couple of really interesting applications for it.
but once you get past those it's not really taking off.
because it doesn't give you a lot to hang on to you have to build whatever you want to build on top of it.
most developers don't have the time or the expertise to do that.
and also you want to be able to leverage other software that has the same idea of what you're communicating about.
so you know with HTTP I can go off and take web servers off the shelf where I can use curl on the client side.
or a web proxy or a web cache.
if I want to scale it out or I can use different services on one and they all talk HTTP.
but with WebSockets you don't have nearly as much to hold on to as it were, and so it's a lot harder to build that value.
I like I always like to point out that I actually considered going from HTTP to WebSockets it downgrade not an upgrade.
even though it's yeah it's an upgrade on that on that you know protocol negotiation kind of thing.
so speaking WebSockets is more capable you can build more than you know.
there are some things you can build on top of WebSockets that you can't build on top of HTTP.
and that's because HTTP imposes constraints, and that's really one of the most interesting things is those constraints.
the the you know the structures that they put on you and how you behave when you're talking to someone else do provide a lot of the value.
you know that you know that the message is going to look like this and that yet means get and post me post and so forth and so on.
if you don't have those constraints it's a wide-open field, but but you have to build it all yourself.
so the constraints simultaneously well constrain you, but they also provide value because they you know have decisions decisions are have already been made for you.
is that is that fair fair description decisions of amending have been made for you and you're building upon those.
you know you're standing on the shoulders of giants as it were.
okay so can you give us a brief history of HTTP of the different versions that were deployed in the wild.
sure so HTTP 0.9 was kind of retro actively named was the first version that that came out of CERN.
and that you know it was literally just a request to get this thing and then you got the response.
there were no headers there was no nothing close the connection start over and do it again.
and so there wasn't really any metadata that wasn't a status code it was very primitive.
and very soon afterwards they decided that it was necessary to have more structure around that to add some of that value.
and so HTTP 1.0 was was kind of developed to the world and then documented in an informational RFC.
I've seen 1945 and it added headers and it added status codes.
and it was very very much influenced by the design of something called mime which is the the protocol for mail for SMTP for getting email around.
but the way that the web uses headers and it uses all these different things is a little bit different from one different enough.
where you can't just take them on library and repurpose it for the web.
so so we call HTTP a mime alike protocol.
and then that was the design of HTTP 1.
HTTP 1 still had a lot of issues especially around how it used the connections underneath the TCP connections the underlying network connections.
and it's especially it was still every time you wanted to request something you know whether it's a sin HTML or an image or what-have-you.
you had to open a new connection wait for that to Sanjay make your request and then close the connection again after you got the response.
and that's horribly inefficient both on the server side in terms of how it manages its resources as well as on the network and how the network is utilized.
and so they built a an extension once the web started to take off once it got really popular and we're talking you know 1994 ish called keepalive.
where you could reuse the connection and then make more than one request on a connection.
and that was pretty much a hack but it worked it had a lot of quarter cases and problems with it.
and so you know what htb really started to take off they decided to make it more formalized and do start work on HTTP 1.1.
and that was done in the IETF in a working group the HTTP working group.
and that spent a couple of years you know working under a tremendous amount of pressure to try.
and document a better version of this protocol that was taking the world by storm.
and so H Depot input one allowed it and formalized this mechanism of keepalive it allowed you to reuse a connection it made some other changes as well.
it had a more formal caching model it had a few other interesting things like HTTP pipelining which unfortunately never really took off.
and then it you know went to market neither it was written down really in a rush because there was such pressure to get it done.
and it was written down by a committee you know I had a lot of different people contributing.
so HTTP 1.1 set up there it became an RFC in the late 90s.
and after that there was an immediate effort to say okay well this is obviously held together by bailing government.
and then and it's that billing wiring and bubblegum and spit and so forth.
and and we need something better something that has more reasonable engineering behind it.
and an effort was started called HTTP NG which was in the w3c.
and it was trying to create a more network friendly binary protocol that used the network more efficiently and had a more a solid architecture behind it.
that never really went anywhere.
I think that the implementers of HTTP after all of this work around HTT 1.1 and all the experts a lot of the experts as well we're pretty exhausted.
and and they'd never really got the energy together to go and come up with this further revision of the HTTP protocol.
so when was that when was HTTP and the HP Envy effort you know was around 2000 I want to say.
that's a great question it was you know so my involvement in standard started around 99.
and 2000 and I think it was just around then that it was really happening.
let's take a look here it had some interesting ideas and there were a few proposals put together.
what's interesting about HTTP ng is is that some of the folks behind that.
including Rick Nielson went on to come up with proposals like pep for the protocol extension protocol I believe.
and and that eventually turned into what became soap and web services which was an interesting right.
but I'm not gonna for people about soap on this interview okay see if we have time at the end I'll see ya.
yeah okay here it is so HTTP ng yeah actually sorry they started out in in mid 97 first drafts in mid 98.
and then by late 99 it was kind of ramping down they realized it wasn't going anywhere I think.
and I didn't directly participate in that stuff I was around the edges a little bit on that but my enrollment came a bit later.
I I chaired some working groups and worked in some working groups kind of around HTTP.
and then in in kind of the mid 2000s 2005-2006 you.
know it became more and more apparent that HTTP was was sort of rudderless.
we didn't have a very strong community around the protocol we didn't have somewhere where all the implementers were discussing the problems that were coming apart.
but but we knew that we were having problems.
I was working for a while on squid the web proxy and seeing a lot of problems in terms of HTTP and our interoperability there.
and so talking to the different implementers in talking to the other stakeholders we decided to start a working group called HTTP bists which is the one that I chair.
and and the idea behind that was just to sit down and read document to write down again what HTTP is.
and so RFC 2616 was the outcome of the HTTP 1.1 effort from that set for many years.
and so what we did was we took it and we picked apart RFC 2616 and we started you know writing down issues.
you know this needs to be clarified that doesn't make any sense this part of the document conflicts with that part of the document.
because remember it was it was written down in in a hurry it was written down by many people.
and and what happened was that throughout the 2000s especially after we had things like Ajax you know XML HTTP requests people started really pushing the boundaries of HTTP protocol.
it wasn't just go off and you know get me some HTML and CSS and eventually JavaScript.
it was you know I maybe post a forum.
it was doing a lot of much more interactive things that really pushed the limits of performance on the protocol as well as the semantics.
in terms of well what is the protocol mean when you combine these different things or how is this corner case handled.
and and so we went to write down these specifications more clearly because we realized that you know people were coming to people like me.
or to Roy fielding or Julian rashke or a few other people asking these questions again and again.
of you know how does this work and we decided to write it down instead.
and so HTTP was turned out to be a multi-year effort we only finished it a little.
while ago I guess what about a year ago a year and a half ago.
and and that's because it was really a part-time project it was you know myself primarily myself and Roy fielding and Julian Raschke taking the time to pick through everything.
and eventually to rewrite the many parts of the specification to modernize it to make it more clear to read.
I was the chair of the working group but I also took editorial responsibility for the caching section.
and I definitely remember you know when I decided to rewrite the section pretty much from scratch.
because I realized that there were certain things that were repeated three or four different times in different parts of the document in three or four slightly different ways.
which is you know it's horrible for interoperability.
and when I was able to do that the first thing I did was ripped something like 10 pages out of the specification.
because there was a repeated you know slightly different text which was very liberating I suppose.
and and so that that's the process we went through there.
in doing so an interesting thing happened we had more.
and more HTTP implementers you know folks from Firefox Chrome Microsoft Apple sometimes you.
know CDN servers would come along and ask questions and get involved.
and and and we slowly started rebuilding the HTTP community.
which you know when you have a protocol that's so critical to the operation of the web it's really good to have the implementers talk to each other.
and so that for me that's kind of the ulterior motive of that work was getting people to talk to each other.
and so we published the RFC 72 72 30 and and its companion documents I blanked out a large part of that.
because it was such a big point about I really was that long ago but I may be but June 2014 here right it wasn't that long at all.
we published those documents and and they collectively redefine HTTP 1.1.
and and so when you you refer to HB 1.1 these documents are the authoritative documents.
you know it's not a new version of HTTP it's just a written down differently.
and we split it up into how many did we end up with the six I think six yeah six different documents we used to have seven.
then we collected it down into six at kind of the last minute.
and and we split it up because you know the RFC format it's it's still in ASCII format there's there's some work on changing that going on right now.
but the option we had was okay we can publish one huge ASCII document and have people try navigate it.
or we can split it up into different logical part and we opted for the ladder.
sometimes you.
know talking to the editors I think sometimes we could have.
and Roy's made this come in a few times we could have just recombined them and published this one document.
it was really picking it apart into the components that was the important thing, and so it's much more modular in that fashion.
so that was a useful so that was there was a huge effort or at least it seemed at that way from the outside.
and it's a huge document or a huge set of documents with it with a huge number of pages.
I don't know how many pages is it like 200 300.
I haven't yeah 26:16 was 200 pages if I remember it was more than 200.
I think the document set is bigger mostly because there's a lot of repeated boilerplate between the documents.
mm-hmm you know there are some things that we had explained in a lot more detail because it was kind of a leiden.
because it didn't fit the use case for the web back in you know the late 90s.
you know 26:16 was published in June 1999 but most the work was done before that substantially before that.
yeah so 26:16 is a hundred and seventy-six pages I think our document said is like someone said 280 290 rings a bell I think.
and like I said a lot of that is repeated boilerplate but it is more navigable it's much more self-explanatory.
and the feedback we've gotten from implementers is is that it's a lot easier to understand how to implement HDPE correctly.
and that was the goal that we had.
so it was a big effort it took a lot of energy sometimes we we have a graph somewhere of kind of you know commit activity on the repo.
and there were definitely a few periods where it was pretty quiet and then Julian and I.
and Roy would get together somewhere you know Roy's house or or in Germany to visit Julian.
and you'd see the spike of activity and then it kind of you know calmed down a bit as we incorporated feedback from other people in a working group.
and talked through everything.
but we got it done I don't think we have a lot of appetite to do that again.
although Julian Julian does want to relatively see and I think take that document set and make it a full standard.
so you know right now the HTTP documents the IETF has gone to a two-level standards process where this proposed standard in full standard.
and their proposed standards or is a draft standard.
I always get next up they change it too often.
but but we want to take them eventually to full standard because you know they're a cornerstone of the way the internet works today.
so when we clean them up a bit and probably when we do a little work to incorporate what happens in HTTP to.
and get a little bit more erratic collective and so forth we'll probably revise these documents one more time and publish them.
mostly in the form you see them today but a few improvements.
the one thing that I'm personally really happy about is that they still read like specs and not like pseudocode as for example the HTML but does these days.
yeah that's a contentious issue then they used to be we definitely added some more of that.
and I do have a lot of sympathy for what the web working grid guys and the html5 guys have done and girls I should say.
in that it is you know it's important for interoperability to specify things as closely as you can.
and and if you do it algorithmically if you say you know you do this let this be this.
and then that is that you really do assure interoperability even around all the corner cases.
on the other hand pretty much unreadable right so that's the down side of things.
well yes you you do have to you know be able to read that and keep the state in your head.
and and so as someone who just wants to casually look at the document.
and say well what's the syntax of this or what does that mean it's a lot harder to do.
I think their response to that would be well this is where the user guides come in or the books or the tertiary material.
and and the point there being that if you you specify it both ways if you say here's the algorithm and here's what it means you know in in prose.
then there's the chance for mismatch and unless you're very very careful about making sure you mark which one is normative.
and you know looking for consistency there it's much more likely you're gonna specify ambiguous things.
or one of your implementers will look at the pros and take something else away and interoperability will suffer.
and and of course with the web often security will suffer.
and so I do have a lot of sympathy for that approach but yeah it sucks it sucks as a reader.
and it's also if you want to reuse an artifact for something else.
if you want to repurpose it into that whole you know an unintended reuse axiom that Tim talked about.
then it's it's a lot harder than that to have unintended to reuse when something is specified as an algorithm like that.
mm-hmm okay so we left through the versions including the new version of HTTP 1.1 which took a long time to be finalized and.
then speedy came along.
yeah so speedy came along I remember I was visiting the San Francisco Bay Area.
and I got an email from someone I didn't know a gentleman named Mike Bell she and he wanted to have dinner with me.
and so I went out and he kind of gave me a tantalizing.
you know I have some interesting stuff about HTTP I want to talk about he worked for Google.
ok so I went out to dinner with Mike and he laid out what he was doing with speedy.
he's you know him and Roberto Piana the two core authors of of speedy.
and I remember vividly just getting a huge smile on my face because what he was talking about made a lot of sense.
and it was so much in line with things that Roy had talked about when he was talking about waka.
so walk-up is a protocol that Roy fielding has talked about for a long time when you know HTTP evolution or replacement protocol but he's never written down unfortunately.
but from you know just being around Roy and talking about it.
I kind of could intuit enough about it to say that what sounds like Mike is in some way is going down the same path.
and and so we you know we did that and he gave me a copy I think of this beliefs back. or or I looked at it when they did the release.
it was this was just a few days before they made the public announcement.
and what intrigued me was that I was able to look at their spec and go and.
and take a Python an HTTP ripe library that I'd written you know from sockets up and rewrite it to to talk speedy.
in you know two days of kind of you know part I'm doing other stuff kind of you know timeframe.
and I was able to interoperate with Crump because they they put it in Crum.
and that to me said wow this is you know amazing it works you can write an interoperable implementation from this back.
and looking at my code you know HTTP 1.1 is a textual protocol.
so it's all you know here's the header field here's a colon and you have to split on the colon and here's the value.
and then there's a new line or maybe it's a slash are slash end and there's another one and there's a blank line and then you have the body.
so you have to do all this parsing to figure out how HTTP 1 works.
and in that parsing there's a lot of error handling or corner cases in that well what if there's whitespace here.
or does capitalization matter there or you know there are all these different kinds of cases you have to handle.
and in fact HTTP 1.1 has four different ways to figure out where one message ends and the next message begins which is incredibly complex.
and so if I looked at the code base for my HTTP 1 implementation versus speeding.
the speedy was a lot more compact it was it was significantly smaller much easy to read more efficient not so forth and so on.
and and so as an implementer that's a joy when you have you know a binary protocol.
yeah that's not great from the standpoint of debugging it because you have to have some tool to help you debug it.
but from an implementer standpoint you're much more confident about your implementation quality if you don't have to worry about all those corner cases and all that text parsing.
when it's just here's the binary and if you get your pardon wrong you're gonna know it because everything's gonna go up in flames.
so let's talk a bit about what what speedy actually improved upon or what problems it addressed.
so one thing that you mentioned now was the is the textual the textual nature of HTTP 1.1, and speedy obviously recast that in the form of binary frames.
so as opposed to as you just explained what else was new in in speedy.
so the the biggest change was that once you have this binary encoding you can split up HTTP messages into those frames.
and each of those frames has what's called an explicit stream identify er.
so an HTTP 1.1 when I have a request at a response there on the same connection.
and I know that that request is associated with the response because of the ordering.
you know I send request number one and then I send request number two.
and I get back response number one and response number two in that order that's just how it works.
but that makes it so that you can't reorder the requests and responses if the server you know can't get response number one.
or it has to think about it a lot or it's really really big.
that means that response number two is blocked until response number one is complete and that's called head-of-line blocking.
and that means that you know for that and a few other reasons.
but mostly that browsers don't just use one TCP connection to talk to a webserver they use somewhere between four and eight connections.
and what they do is they use those multiple connections for parallelism they'll say okay I'm going to put this request on that connection.
and in case that blocks I'll use this other connection for the next request.
the problem with that is is that if you look at the statistics you know an average web page these days can have somewhere around.
or even more than a hundred different things to load.
JavaScript CSS libraries images there's a lot going on in the modern web.
and if you've only got between four and eight connections that means you still as a browser have to make choices about which connection you use for which request.
and at what time and how to order them.
and so the browser's use a whole bunch of heuristics to figure that out and usually actually surprisingly often they get it they do a pretty good job.
but often they can't because they don't have enough information.
what HTTP to does is is because you now have this stream identifier where you can explicitly associate a request in response.
you know you know that they're related because of this little identifier.
and because you can chop up requests and responses into frames so you don't have to keep you know one request all together.
you can interleave requests and responses and parts of requests and responses at will in both directions on the connection.
so now all this it's what we call a fully multiplex protocol where you can send any part of any request or response at any time.
you know as you've got these buffers you need to drain and that frees up that net had a blind blocking problem. and so that's a lot better.
the goal in in in speeding and eventually http/2 is to only have browsers use one connection to talk to a given web server.
and so that's the really big change in speed again and later in htb to.
the other interesting things are that if you look at traces of modern page loads you'll notice that there's a lot of repeated information in HTTP headers in both directions.
and that has a negative impact on performance as well especially on the requests side.
if request headers with things like cookies get really big then it takes longer to even get the requests to the server so the server can start serving them.
and so speeding introduced a header compression where you can actually just compress the headers as they're being pushed out on the wire.
and so that's separate from we're compressing the bodies by the way.
there's what happens is there's a compression context just for the headers on all all the headers on the connection in one direction and that gets reused for every request.
so that you can learn what headers are common on that connection.
if you send a cookie once you don't have to send it again you can refer to the cookie you send the first time.
mm-hmm so obviously Google had that started doing this for for their own purposes.
so so they had a they obviously benefit from the protocol being more efficient given that they run they probably run the largest set of servers in the world.
so um one of the things that I seem to recall is that they actually deployed it in.
and tried it out before telling the world about it is that correct recollection.
they had it running on GFE which is the Google front-end server.
Mike worked for chrome and Roberta work for GFE so they were working together that's that was a collaboration between them.
then they brought data you know they brought data to the table took we think that this is interesting enough to talk about with the community.
and and so I think it was the following year that came Matt came to an IETF meeting.
and I gave him some time their working group meeting to present what he'd found.
and to kind of give the heads up to every one community that you know this work was going on.
I mean obviously unless people know about it but it was important to get the conversation going the working group.
and then a little while past that I think the next probably notable thing that happened was that Firefox shipped an implementation of speedy as well.
and and that's really when people set up and took notice.
they realize that this isn't just a Google thing.
if the engineers at Firefox thought that this was interesting enough to spend their time on implementing that that's a really big statement.
you know we we saw interest from other folks we saw eventually implementations from folks like Ingenix and and and and other servers.
and and it was very clear that momentum was building.
so you know from the standard standpoint we had a choice we could either let speedy become a de facto standard in the marketplace.
where you know whatever Google said it would become it would become.
or we could try to bring it into the standards bodies and and have a wider community of folks take a look at it and give their input.
and make sure that it reflected more people's needs.
and and so talking to folks inside of the ITF we thought that was a good idea to try to do that talking to her toe.
and Mike they were willing to bring it to the table.
I think Firefox was encouraging them to do that quite strongly.
and and so we ended up holding a process where we said right we're thinking that it you know we see enough in implement our interest.
and deployment interest in a newer version of a protocol to serve the needs of HTTP.
that we want to start talking about that in the working group does anybody have any proposals for that sort of thing.
and we ended up having three we had speedy from Mike and Roberto we had a proposal from Microsoft.
and we had a proposal from I guess three or four intermediary implementers so folks who make web proxies or reverse proxies.
and the working group talked about that for a while speedy was by far the that was you know most well specified.
and fully fleshed out and had experience behind it.
and also it had the most support by all the implementers who came so we chose speedy is as the basis of the work.
but when we did that we we rewrote the Charter to start work on HTTP to using speed ease the basis.
and we were very careful to point out that it's not you know choosing speedy by default it is this is the starting point.
and we're going to talk about everything in this document and we're going to make sure that the working group agrees on everything in the document.
and if the working group doesn't agree we'll pull it out or if the working group comes up with a better way to do it we'll put it in. and so we were chartered to do that.
I wanted to keep a fairly aggressive schedule for standards we charted to do it in about two years.
that's a very aggressive four standards work and it's glacially slow by most developers standpoint.
but but trust me that's that's fast four standards.
well if it's if it's compared to the time it took you to get HTTP 1.1 revised I'm sure that's that it's really fast.
because it was much faster to do a new protocol than to revise the old one right right.
well yeah and that's kind of apples and oranges just because that was a very much a part-time effort.
that was you know a bunch of us on the side saying uh what do you think about this does this make sense.
and nor is HTTP two had a lot of momentum behind it you know there was a lot of very strong implementer interest.
we had a lot of resources put into it from the get-go.
so so we charted to do it in two years and and I did that really my argument in in that kind of schedule was.
we've got a tremendous amount of implement or interest they've come to the standards bodies in good faith put some of their really talented engineers up for it.
if we take five years of argument committee about this or ten years.
or you know there are lots of examples like that we will lose their interest and they'll walk away.
and that means that the effort will be dominated by people who have opinions but not running code.
so we kept it time limited to make sure that we you know could could have that audiences full attention for a bounded amount of time.
and have their input and turn it into the best document we could.
and so it took about two years we started working earnest I guess in December.
and the next June July we had I think our second or perhaps third face-to-face meeting in Hamburg.
and and that was our first what we said was an inter Aquaman you know we put out a few drafts before then.
but this was the first time we said okay here's the draft and we think this is good enough for people to go off and actually do an implementation of.
and we'll do interoperability on on on that and do some testing at our next meeting.
and so people had six weeks or so to come up with an implementation and I was hoping we'd see maybe three implementations show up in Humber.
and we ended up having ten which that's what I really knew we were onto something.
I knew that that this was not just committee working a bunch of people sitting around a table talking.
this was a serious effort where people were writing real code.
and so that you know that was a really good sign to me that made me feel a lot better about it.
and then we spent the next year and a half on a bit of a rollercoaster and hammering out the document.
we had to rip out the compression mechanism that speedy used because it wasn't safe they found an attack against it.
and then we had a competition effectively to choose a new one that with a few different proposals ended up being combined.
went to last call last year had a bunch of people raised a bunch of fairly big issues about it at that last minute.
and so we had to talk through those that took a few months came to conclusions about it that you know people were a lot of people were unhappy about.
and I think you know the rule of thumb is is that when everyone's unhappy you know that that's consensus.
and took it to the iesg late last year the isg is the body in the ITF that formally makes decisions and approves documents.
it's a council if you will of people who run the different areas in the organization.
and they have all been approved it as we speak so I'm hoping that we'll have an RFC on HP due pretty soon.
okay so we could we can probably assume or we can hope that it'll be an official document of an official standard.
well as much as official standards are released by the ITF by the time I'll listen let's listen to this to this episode I can only hope so.
so two different you know endings for this if you like with it it's fine this way.
so let's talk a bit about the technical stuff we haven't touched upon so.
but for first of all maybe we can we maybe we could finalize this discussion about a speedy and HTTP.
so for for all for all purposes we can assume that that speedy will be will be so sumed or superseded by HTTP -.
it seems that even Google has has the greet or Google has agreed to that as well.
so the goal is to to go with HTTP to only correct.
yeah you know early 2015 they've been telegraphing that intent to the working group for a very long time.
that their intention is to move to http to as the standard.
so that that's not a big surprise I think for most of us in the working group but it's really good to see.
I think they announce they're gonna turn it off in early 2016 so we'll see if they meet that schedule.
changing protocols in on the server side is always kind of a nightmare.
so you know if they don't meet that by the day I'm not going to be horribly disappointed.
the momentum behind h-2b - is is pretty clear so we're pretty confident gonna get a good chance in the marketplace.
ok so we talked about some significant changes so the the reuse of a single connection is one the binary of all the header compression was one.
is there anything else that's new in HTTP - as opposed to HTTP 1.1.
another thing that's worth touching on is server push.
the the idea that the server can push a response to the client.
usually you can think of it as the server pushing something into the clients cache before the client realizes it needs it.
and that's just to avoid the round trip you know you think about when you load a page the client goes and gets some HTML.
the server sends back the HTML and parses it for all the links and then starts requesting all the different link to objects.
but if you think about that the server just set the HTML.
it knows what links are in that what can it just start sending what it thinks the client is going to need.
and so server pushes an optimization to try and avoid that round trip.
I think most people would be happy to admit that it's the most experimental part of HTTP -.
how it's going to be used in in real life is still a bit of an unknown.
it's especially uncertain because it's the one part of HTTP - that.
really requires you know it doesn't fit into a normal HTTP one API.
so everything else in HTTP - you can you can map on to an HTTP API.
and when I did my library you know you use the same API for the client in the server you're still using HTTP methods.
and headers and bodies and status codes and everything there none of that changes.
it's just how it gets put onto the wire is different.
but with server push it's it's a different thing it's the server sending a symptom it's kind of like sending a synthetic request response pair to the client proactively.
and how that's gonna get put into code and people are gonna think about it how it's gonna be used we'll see it'll be interesting.
I know that an HTTP 1.1 there were a lot of kind of last-minute or you know extra features put on that didn't work out in the end.
because they weren't mapped well onto the existing code basis things like pipelining or the expect continued function they've never really worked well.
and personally I think that part of the reason why they've never worked well is.
because they were tacked on to the protocol like that they weren't they didn't fit within the core base the core part of the protocol.
so I would assume that for the client it should be pretty easy to you reuse the same API correct.
because they just they just get invited to a question they haven't asked yet so if they ask can they get the answer.
but on the server side it's obviously different it's definitely different cuz you have to push and that's kind of a new thing.
on the client side it could be the same it could be that it gets pushed into your local cache you know look it's already there that's great.
but people are already talking about ways to use or maybe abuse server push to do other things to kind of build a venting on top of HTTP. and your server pushed events.
and that means that you do need something to get a notification so we'll see.
I I think it's it's fascinating to see how it's going to be used it could fizzle.
and turn into something that is only used for corner cases it could be the basis of a lot of exciting new stuff.
I think we're just going to see.
so the one question I always have about this feature is what if I don't want the server to push the stuff because I'm not using it.
so yes you can turn it off so you can either turn off altogether and say I'm not participating in server push don't push me stuff.
and if you do I'm gonna shut down the connection.
you can also refuse a push you can say okay the server starts pushing you something does it push promise you can say okay I already have that my cache.
or maybe I'm a web spider I don't need it.
and you reset the stream and that's one of them actually one of the new bonus features an HP -.
that's really good in HTTP one if let's say you start a big download you know or you're getting something quite sizable from the server.
if all of a sudden you don't need it you know maybe the users never get it away from the page.
or maybe you know they cancel a download or whatever.
you have no choice but to shut down that connection you know you have to eat all the bytes they're being sent to you.
in HD - you have a mechanism called reset stream whereby you can say.
you know what that stream that that one request response interaction I'm not interested in it anymore shut it down.
and you can do that without sacrificing the entire connection.
so that that's good from a performance standpoint because you know you don't have to reconnect with TCP.
if you're on HTTPS you don't have to do a new the SSL negotiation you can still just reuse that connection and get the most out of it.
so reset stream is helpful there and you can use that if somebody starts pushing you something you can say no I don't want that one.
so in terms of terminology the the stream you're talking about is basically the virtual connection right.
what used to be the connection HP one that one it becomes a stream in HTTP - is that mapping is.
it's the connection in HTTP 1.0 without keepalive it really just does identify a single request response pair and that's it.
okay understood Thanks.
good so um one of the reasons again that is something that I seem to recall and I'm happy if you can correct me if it's wrong.
the a signal recall that one of the reasons Google was able to put to try out speedy and practice was that they simply used or mandated TLS for everything.
so everything was encrypted and nobody could tell what they were doing and know it no intermediary was confused by any anything weird going over that HTTP connection.
Brian house house house they're done in speedy versus the way it's done in HTTP -.
and is it mandatory in HTTP - as well as it was in in speedy.
right so yeah it's pretty used to TLS for a couple of different reasons.
one was interoperability as you say in that there are a lot of boxes out on the internet.
that when they see something on port 80 they assume that it's HTTP 1.1 and that assumption to make things break and really awkward in unpredictable ways.
so you get much better interoperability from those middle boxes if your encrypted.
the other reason is is that even even back then you know in 2009 when Mike and Roberto were working on speedy.
there were a number of attacks on the web where you know passwords authentication tokens personal identifying information were going in the clear.
there was an attack called Firesheep where you could go into a you know cafe and turn on this piece of software as a little firefox plugin.
and sniff people's passwords going buying or their authentication tokens for places like Flickr or Yahoo or Facebook or whatever.
and then log in as them and become that person in your browser.
and that's because people weren't using SSL they weren't encrypting their connections.
there were also incidents like I think in Germany Google had the Street View incident.
where they were accidentally for some value of accidentally sniffing Wi-Fi passwords as they did their Street View you know drive around the neighborhoods.
and that data was captured and and that was not good as well.
and and so when they thought about this I think especially Mike took a somewhat principled position said that look we've got this new protocol.
and it can can level the performance issues with using HTTPS to a very large degree or.
even provide better performance over TLS than in HTTP 1.1 without it.
it seems like a great opportunity to level up security in the web to hold out as a carrot and say if you want to use this new protocol.
you know for all of those reasons and as well as for the interoperability reason we're only going to implement it over HTTPS.
and this was all pre Snowden you know that Snowden happened afterwards.
and so that was for speedy and that made a lot of sense we had that constraint kind of grandfathered in implicitly when we took on HTV too.
but it wasn't explicit in the spec and we started to talk about those issues and and whether we should require HTTPS to use HTTP two.
and in fact you know Snowden happened during that one of the big Snowden leaks happened the day before one of our working group meetings in Berlin.
and we quickly kind of reconfigured our agenda to talk about that and what that meant for for HTTP because they were targeting HTTP explicitly.
in the end after a lot of discussion there were enough people in the working group who said well you know HTTP is used for the web sure.
it's also used for a lot of other things it's also used for back-end systems and for api's and for you know non-critical data in their views.
and we couldn't get consensus to require HTTPS for HTTP two because of that there were there are enough people who felt that way.
and and critically you know as working group chair I didn't really have a mechanism.
to make a judgment call about it you know we you know the ITF we say we have rough consensus.
and running code and we make decisions based upon technical criteria.
we didn't at that time have the technical mechanisms in place to say that you know what encryption is something we really need to provide as a baseline requirement.
the other factor there was that our Charter said that we had to be h-2b to had to be usable for all existing uses of HTTP.
and that would include HTTP or our eyes you know we have a technique that we've talked about to encrypt optimistically or opportunistically encrypted HTTP your eyes. but that was controversial as well.
and so we were in this place where we didn't really have a clear way to meet our Charter.
and and to make a technical decision where we could go and say yes let's let's make HTTP to encrypted.
at the same time you know Firefox and Chrome had made very strong statements that they would only be supporting this over TLS. chrome has said only HTTPS.
Firefox has said we'll do HTTPS and and we're going to fool around with the opportunistic security mechanism and try that because we think it's an interesting thing.
but but neither of them are going to do it and clear other browsers haven't made those statements.
but between the two of them they have a tremendous amount of the web browser market and that can actually change the dynamics of the overall deployment of the protocol.
and so you know we were faced with a choice we can either spend six.
or eight months maybe a year maybe delay the protocol indefinitely trying to hash out some sort of compromise position or consensus around encryption on HTTP.
or we could let the market sort it out knowing that these browsers are making their own decisions already.
and and it seemed like the pragmatic thing to do was the latter.
and then so that's where we we left it having said that you know I personally would have loved to have seen it become encrypted only.
and we've been doing work in other places to try and improve the quality of encryption on the web and indeed.
and so the other body I mentioned the beginning of the technical architecture group.
we just released what we call a tag finding a kind of an architectural statement saying that we need to secure the web.
so if we can't you know attack this problem from the standpoint of making HTTP to encrypted in the standards we're looking at in the w3c.
how do we encourage more use of encryption how do we level the playing field so that encryption is easy to use so forth and so on.
and so we're making progress in that front like I can understand some of the reluctance and accepting a TLS only or encryption only way of doing things.
because of the the communication between back-end servers that just happen to use HTTP where no.
okay you know and that was one of the argument that came up again and again and it was interesting to see the you know that argument would be made.
when a few weeks later the new Snowden release would be made where I could say oh look we've gotten into these back-end servers yeah.
and all the sudden addiction becomes more important.
fair enough so one of the things that I again seem to recall is that Google used some hack with speedy to initiate the SSL or the speedy connection.
how has that been affected by the standardization made should be -.
first of all is it correct and and what happened to it.
so there's a couple of ways that you can initiate HTTP -.
for for speedy they had two mechanisms one was if you're already on an HTTP URL they used what was called NPN our next protocol negotiation.
which is a modification to the TLS handshake or an extension of the TLS handshake.
which says when you you finish the TLS handshake and have a secure connection the next protocol we want to talk inside of that connection is this one.
and that's how you can advertise support for HTTP tool or for speedy an HTTP to has a similar mechanism.
it's just gone through the standards process it's it's a little bit different in its properties but it's called a LPN or application layer protocol negotiation.
and that's an open SSL now it's getting more prevalent.
the other mechanism for discovering and.
negotiating negotiating speedy was alternate protocol which is an HTTP header that you would get the kind of Henson says that.
if you want to talk this new protocol you can do it over on this port over here on that same server.
and we have a very similar mechanism that's a little more general and usable for other things called alternative services which we still have as a draft in the world. and we're working on stuff.
okay so maybe let's talk a bit about the consequences.
so we we kind of assumed or it was kind of the unspoken assumption that if you do.
if you switch to HTTP two you get some benefit in terms of efficiency and speed.
what what is actually the basis for that assumption where there's tests made and I've said what what are the results and what can what can users expect.
it's hard to quantify it it depends so much about how on how you use the protocol and how the browser implements the protocol.
the early feedback I've gotten from most of the implementers is that generally speaking you'll see somewhere between a five.
and fifteen percent performance improvement just by turning the protocol on.
and that's not for every connection but it's for most connections there will be cases where you won't see any improvement or it might even be a tiny bit worse.
and there have been a few interesting academic papers out there about that and how that works.
the interesting part comes when you tune your your web content a little bit to take advantage of it and you tune your web server.
so you know we have all these different techniques in for performance optimization in HTTP 1.1.
and if you you know if you participated in the web performance community.
over the last couple of years the conferences like velocity the mantra has always been reduced the number of requests you make.
and that's because there's so much overhead to requests in HTTP 1.1 because the browser might have to split up a new connection.
or that request might be blocked by another request before it or vice-versa.
yeah yeah so what's happened is is that there are a bunch of what are effectively hacks that we use for performance optimization in HTTP 1.1.
in that you know we have things like CSS inlining CSS spriting concatenation of different parts of JavaScript into one big download.
and all of that is you know to fulfill this matter.
we here in a web performance optimization community which is reduced the number of requests you know avoid that overhead of an individual request.
well in HTTP 2 you don't have the overhead nearly as much you have multiplexing so you don't have to worry about that blocking.
and you don't have the massive headers for each request you know you have had a compression that are that are making those much much smaller.
and as a result you know individual requests don't have nearly as much over and it's almost not noticeable.
and so if you phase out those those hacks you can tune the performance of your site back to something that that's more interactive and and smoother.
on the anecdotal evidence I'm getting is as often performance with HC b2 is is smoother.
there there's less variation from load to load you know it's it's just a better experience for the end user.
so so 5 to 15% is kind of the guideline number you'll get it as a rough starting point.
then you get folks who are doing a lot of optimization and really building their sites to take advantage of the new protocol.
you know Google has cited numbers of around a forty to forty four percent performance increase especially on high latency connections.
I think Twitter had I think similar numbers twitter was different because they weren't using speedy and HTTP to a lot in their mobile clients.
so this wasn't a browser client this is you know a mobile app that has been in the HTTP requests.
but if you think about it if you're requesting a lot of information you know through an API.
and you can make it a lot more granular because there's not an overhead to the requests you can get much better performance than using HTTP 1.1.
so that kind of makes sense I think we'll see over time.
I I'm expecting that as the protocol gets deployed we'll see more best practices to matter.
the web performance community will have more tools to analyze performance and then a better understanding of how to get the best out of it.
and the open source implementations will continually improve themselves so that we have a decent out-of-the-box performance.
a lot of what HTTP 2 does is you know I talked before about all the heuristics.
the browser uses to decide which request to make it what time on what connection.
well the idea in HT 2 is is that as much as possibly move those heuristics out of the browser.
the browser isn't trying to predict how the page is going to perform it all gets put onto the server.
and the browser sends information about how the page is loading in the form of what we call priorities.
but the server makes the decision about what response to send and what time and what proportion and how to prioritize those.
and and a lot of I think the potential benefit is is in terms of you know those decisions that the servers make.
so it's kind of taking performance out of the browser hands at least partially and then giving it over to the server to make its own decisions.
so you mentioned those hacks that people have been using for a long time to make HTTP 1.1 faster for for websites.
is it correct that those hacks actually hurt you when you're using HTTP 2.
they certainly don't help you you think about it if you're downloading a very large JavaScript library because it's all been concatenated together.
and you're only executing you know 10% of it for the actual page then then that's inefficient.
you know you because you know the word from the browser standpoint.
while you're loading that javascript unless you're doing an async load the world stops and certainly why you execute it.
well you know the world stops and that's bad for performance.
also if you want to change part of you know your CSS sprite or your JavaScript you know there's just one one you need to change or one image.
then again because it's all lumped together in the HTTP cache you have to invalidate the entire cache and read download it.
one way to think about it is is that you know what we've kind of been doing slowly but surely is turning the web into these single page apps.
and I don't mean that in the sense that it's just a single page that you navigate I mean something more like flash or or PDF.
where you have to download this huge chunk of stuff just to get a functional page and and that's not a very web like experience.
you know PDF has the ability to navigate it has linking you could build a web out of PDF.
but nobody really does that because it's so clunky and you have to wait so long for things to load.
HTTP to has the promise that we can make things more granular again.
so in for practical purposes it'll obviously take some time until well first of all HTTP 2 is finalized then until it becomes part of the browser's.
and then until those browser's gain significant market share so HTTP 1 that well it's obviously there to stay from a long time right.
so what is the what is the way to deal with that do people do you expect people to build for both.
or built primarily for HTTP 2 and for HTTP 101 only for backward purposes.
or doesn't doesn't it really matter as much as I make it sound a little faster than you think.
in that both Chrome and Firefox have a code ready to go.
Firefox is very excited about this.
I think both of them are at the point where they just have to change the protocol identifier.
in the negotiation from the draft to the final version.
and then put it through their release processes and you know we have easy amacrine browsers now where you know they're releasing every six weeks.
and so we'll see them upgrade quite quickly.
I know that the IE team is very impatient to match or at least get in the ballpark with those kinds of schedules that they want to compete there too.
and so we're I think we're going to see in a personal part of the browser market moved to the new protocol quite quickly.
having said that yeah there is gonna be no row hat period there were always gonna be servers out there that you know run HTTP 1.1 and that's fine.
from a server operator you know from web performance standpoint I think we're gonna see a number of different strategies based on the needs and the capabilities of the sites.
some sites will just leave it all spread it in in Lund and concatenate it until it's.
so obvious that they need to switch over based on their metrics let us do it one day.
some sites will do it proactively and take the performance hit for the old browsers.
and some folks will you know put a feo solution in front.
or some sort of intermediary that you know makes the decision on the fly and andrey encodes the pages.
you know whether it's you know much paid mod pagespeed or whatever to serve the client each individual client as best they can.
well it'll be interesting to see which strategies give the best results.
ok maybe a final question all this work you've been doing within the HTTP working group in the past years has been sort of under the hood right.
first the revision of a specification without actually updating the protocol.
and then updating the protocol but mostly updating it in a way that makes it completely transparent to the actual plication developers right.
so they have been different kinds of changes are not not downplaying in an effort the huge effort and it's a huge achievement.
but do you expect something to change in the actual protocol semantics anytime soon.
are we looking at new verbs or a new optimization or any other more significant rate to http.
or is it here to stay the way it is for a looong time.
ah that's a great question you know there's there's that kind of semantic footprint that HTTP has a request.
and a response and the request has a method and the response has a status code.
and you've got headers and none of your right none of that has changed.
you know we've we've checked on a few headers down again occasionally we have a new status code or we have a new method like patch.
but but it's still very recognizable you know from the API you use and so forth.
I've been talking to a bunch of folks in the community about you know what next steps might be.
now there are a bunch of intermediate proposals for things like new status codes whether it's the four five ones that's good the timbre is proposed.
or or some other stuff.
I think we're going to continuously see that you know low level add an extension point kind of stuff.
but I've also heard some people interested in okay what would the benefit be if we started fresh.
and we said what does it take for a browser to load a web page what does it need from a protocol.
and and what benefits could we do if we started from scratch.
I don't think we're gonna see that any time saving but it's an interesting thought experiment to see where that might lead.
so what is a good way for listeners to start familiarizing themselves with the whole topic is it to read the HTTP to spec.
or do you have another any other good starting points people could look at.
starting points so on the HTTP to home page there's a it's HTTP - not github that I oh there's a FAQ there that's probably a good place to start.
and there's also a section on the home page what is HTTP -.
another great resource is Daniel Steinberg who's the the main author of curl I hope everybody knows where all has gone.
and written a an HTTP to guide kind of a primer.
and it's a PDF on his website that is a really fantastic resource he's been updating it as we've we've gone along.
Daniels participating the working group as well and he's been a great participant.
and so you kind of get this fly-on-the-wall perspective on why the protocol is the way it is how to use it what it is how it works.
and that's a great introduction I think.
excellent so Marc it's been a pleasure talking to you thanks a lot for all those insights.
and no worries yeah thanks for doing this.
thanks so much this is Stefan tilaka for software engineering radio thank you for listening.
thanks for listening to se radio an educational program brought to you by I Triple E software magazine.
for more information about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at se - radio -.
to provide feedback you can write comments on each episode on the website or write a review on iTunes mention a message us on Twitter at se radio.
or search for the software engineering radio group on LinkedIn Google+ or Facebook.
you can also email us at team at se - radio net.
this and all other episodes of SU radio is licensed under the creative commons two-point-five license. thanks again for your support.
[Applause]
[Music]
you.